Coming to the end
of the Petri net
chapter, I would like to talk
through one or two examples with you.
These are
examples which once
again illustrate typical
scenarios or modeling patterns.
By "modeling patterns" I don't
mean anything formal like the
formally defined properties
we have seen.
But simply certain approaches, how
one can handle typical situations
in dynamic systems
with Petri net modeling.
Some of this
we've already seen.
In particular, this short video is
going to be about mutual exclusion.
And you've basically already seen that in
the water gate example in the practice exercises (actually, this will happen on the next sheet).
There were also some modeling
patterns in the afternoon example.
What I had discussed in the lecture and had
developed in the pipe tool as a Petri net.
For example, sources and
sinks were used: Transitions that
have no pre-
or post-weight points.
Or we saw snares
with a specific purpose,
namely to guard
certain points or transitions.
So guard points, with
which you can make
sure that certain transitions are
only fireable under certain constellation.
You could just look
back at that example.
Or, for example, the capacity
bounds, that is, attempts to express
with Petri nets that certain places must not
contain more than a certain number of tokens.
Not because the Petri net
is bounded as a formal
property, but because it is
already brought in during modeling that
certain places must not contain more
than a certain number of tokens.
This is per se not given
when creating the Petri net, such restrictions.
This last aspect, constraining
capacity or the ability to
specify bounds, we're not going
to look at in this video.
This will be
about mutual exclusion.
In that sense, this is the second
to last video of the Petri net chapter.
The other will then be the
last video of the Petri net chapter.
Let's first deal with the
concept of mutual exclusion, in
English "mutual exclusion", therefore called mutex
(the place we use for it).
The scenario here is
as follows, and this could
be very generally
applicable in various situations.
We somehow consider at least two
actors (in the case times exactly two
actors), each having
a critical range.
This somehow means
an execution area,
an action area, which they
each want to enter secured alone.
In this sense, the
"critical" should be that
not both actors should be in
the critical area at the same time.
So it is to be prevented that the actors
come at the same time into their respective area.
Because they could obstruct
each other there or
an undesirable behavior
could be the consequence.
So let's imagine that the two actors
are programs working on the hard disk.
The critical area could be writing to
a certain file, and we don't want both
actors to try to write to
the same file at the same time.
Therefore, there should always be at
most one actor in this critical area.
How can we think of
this as a Petri net design?
We might have two Petri nets,
for one actor and for the other.
I have stylized
the system quite simply:
We simply imagine one
actor represented by this Petri
net and the second actor
represented by this Petri net.
In reality, there could be
larger Petri nets behind each.
So it could be that what is here
only one place, is in reality a whole
Petri net, in which something goes in, something
comes out (and what happens in here doesn't matter).
It doesn't have to
be exactly one spot.
That would be
the non-critical area.
So somehow a Petri
net part, where any actions
can be executed, which have nothing
to do with the critical area.
The same is
true for actor 2.
So that's
non-critical area
1 and non-critical area
2 for the two actors.
And then there's also a
critical area for each actor, and
let that be K1,
K2 for those two actors.
And the idea is that that's the
area that should somehow be prevented from both
being there at
the same time.
So it should
be prevented that
at the same time, for example, a
token is here and a token is here.
Because that would mean that both actor 1
and actor 2 are in their critical area.
So if we consider these actions k1, k2,
nk1, nk2 as "actor 1 enters its critical
area", "actor 2 enters its
critical area" and analogously respectively for
leaving the critical area and
entering the non-critical area, then certain
sequences of actions should not be
possible for the common overall system.
So it should not be possible: k1, k2,
i.e. actor 1 enters the critical area, and before
actor 1 has left the critical area,
actor 2 also enters its critical area.
Because if that then meant
that both actors were trying
to write to a file, they could
accidentally do so at the same time.
And of course the water gate example
from the exercise is quite similar.
That is about ships that are not supposed to be
in a certain part of the water gate at the same time.
That ultimately has to do
with critical area as well.
How could
this be solved?
The Petri net, as stylized here,
of course has the property that it
would be quite possible to execute k1
and k2 directly one after the other.
Can we
prevent this?
One can use a
kind of guard place.
That is, an additional place which itself has no
functionality in the sense of actors 1 and 2.
But it ensures that certain
undesired behavior does not occur.
It is possible to synchronize via an
extra place, which is called a mutex place.
This is an auxiliary unit, which is
often called mutex because of "mutual exclusion".
And what is
the procedure here?
This is a place with
a token at the beginning.
And this token
is always needed
when one of the two
actors enters its critical area.
So, for example, if actor 1
wants to enter his critical area, then,
of course, somehow the
non-critical area has to be
left, but in addition, this mutex
place has to be occupied with a
token, which actor 1 then consumes
in order to enter his critical area.
That is, to join the
critical area (i.e., to bring the
token from here to here),
this token must additionally be consumed.
Which also means that then, for
example, directly afterwards the second actor
cannot enter
its critical area.
Because that would mean executing k2, but
that also depends on this mutex location.
Let's assume
that k1 fires.
Then this and this token
would disappear, here would be a
token, actor 1 would work
through his critical area and would
not release the token for the
mutex until the critical area is left.
So when actor 1 crosses
back over into the non-critical area,
that is, leaves
its critical area.
Then this token
would be returned and
could be reused by
k1 or by k2.
Intuitively, this synchronization across this
common point ensures that both
actors cannot be in the
critical region at the same time.
This is, of course, based on
the fact that there is a conflict.
The respective transitions k1 and
k2 here are both activated in
the situation shown, but
just not activated concurrently.
But we have a conflict
exactly over this position here.
This prevents them both
from entering their critical area.
That would be the
informal and intuitive reasoning.
Of course, you can look
at this again formally by
just inspecting
the reachability graph.
We want to show that there is never a
token in places K1 and K2 at the same time.
How can
we show this?
We can plot
the reachability graph.
I just did that without
developing that step by step.
So we see here, if
we take the place order NK1,
K1, K2, NK2 (so basically the way the
places were plotted here from left to right as
well), then we know
the start marking is (1,0,1,0,1).
We can see
that about here.
And then, in
each case, it is
drawn which transitions are executable and what
the markings reached by them look like.
We can actually see here, for one thing, that
there are no sequences of the kind k1, k2.
If k1 was executed, then before
k2 can be executed, always at
least once more
nk1 must be executed.
That is
one observation.
And the other observation is indeed
that among the markings reachable here at
all, there is none where both
K1 and K2 contain a 1.
Here, respectively, the two interesting places
K1, K2 are marked in bold.
And there is simply no reachable marking where
there is a 1 here and here respectively.
The mutex place has
successfully achieved that here.
That would be the
simplest example for mutual exclusion.
And as I said, it shows up
in many examples and applications of Petri nets.
One might
also ask:
Where would this have
helped us in the past?
And well, actually also in the example
before in the context of the Feeding
Philosophers one can make
use of mutual exclusion.
At least one
can see this very
easily if one simplifies the
problem and considers only two philosophers.
In general, one could also
look for solutions for larger constellations
of dining philosophers,
following such synchronization ideas.
I discuss this now
only for the simplest case.
We look at
the feeding philosophers.
We just did that recently, so
I don't need to discuss that further.
We'll look
at the simplification
that we sent one
of the three philosophers home.
So there are only
two dining philosophers left.
We see that
down here as well.
So philosopher 3 is
gone and it's one less
fork (otherwise the problem
wouldn't be as interesting).
But we now have P1,
P2 and the intervening F1, F2.
Now you could have them sit down
a little differently, facing each other, etc.
But that doesn't
change the problem.
The problem
is that
there are still deadlocks
in the simplified Petri net.
That is, even here
it can happen that
P1, P2 starve because they
behave in an unfavorable way.
By both grabbing the right fork and
then not being able to eat, nor
being able to put the forks back because
they have to grab the left fork first.
Also here in this Petri
net a deadlock is still possible.
So maybe synchronization
could help us there.
So we can try
to introduce an extra mutex
site that somehow prevents, for example,
P1 and P2 from both grabbing exactly
one fork and then not being
able to get the second fork.
Maybe as a quarrel,
you can actually solve the
problem here at the application level, so
to speak, without an extra mutex place.
Namely if one makes
the mental leap to say:
How would it be, then, if
the two philosophers changed their behavior slightly?
Namely, one could make one of
them a left-handed person, that is,
prescribe a
change of handedness.
What would
that look like?
Here I made P1
a left-handed person right away.
That is, P1's behavior
would no longer be
to grab the right fork first
and then wait for the left.
But to grab the left fork first
and then wait for the right one.
This is expressed here in the
Petri net by simply bending two arrows.
In each case the arrows, where the philosopher
1 takes access to the forks 1 and 2.
They were bent exactly in such a
way that the arrow, which led before
from F2 to something at the philosopher 1,
now instead comes from where F1 was before.
So exactly these two
arrows now run crosswise.
Now I claim that
this solves the problem.
Why?
This leads to the fact that now
not both reach first for the right fork,
but P1 for the left
and P2 for the right.
That is, this fork F1 would now be
the one grabbed first for both of them.
And that ultimately makes it
a synchronization point or mutex point.
How can we
convince ourselves of this?
We could diagram the Petri net again in
a different way to make it more obvious.
Now this is a little asymmetrical
because I removed the third philosopher.
We can represent exactly
the same Petri net by
shaking it a bit
and rearranging the nodes.
Now, you'll either have to believe me or
compare it on the slides side by side,
that this is the same Petri
net as this one (just painted differently).
So exactly
the same connections.
And here it becomes now more obvious
that the F1-place acts like a mutex.
This Petri net, as it is
shown here, is free of deadlock.
You can take my word for that, or
play it out, or plot the reachability graph.
The point is that
here both P1 and P2,
to be filled, must each
fire this or that transition.
And they
both access F1.
That is, if, for example, philosopher 1
reaches for his left fork (after F1),
then this very token
would disappear up here.
And then philosopher 2 is practically
paralyzed and can only become active again
when philosopher 1 has put down
this fork again, i.e. has eaten.
This is a
conflict of course.
That is, these two transitions are in
conflict with respect to the fork F1.
This was just not the
case in the original philosopher problem.
There, at the beginning, the actions
of reaching for the right fork were
concurrent for
all three philosophers.
Which sounds nice at
first, since it is parallel.
But that led to a deadlock,
while here by this introduction of the
conflict, the mutual exclusion,
this mutex-place, it is finally
ensured that not simply both philosophers
reach wildly for the first fork.
But only one of them can do that,
and afterwards the other one cannot do anything immediately.
But when philosopher 1 has finished eating,
philosopher 2 can take his turn again.
That is, here we
prevent deadlock by synchronization, by
using this
mutex site ultimately.
This is a very typical
modeling pattern in various applications.